great so now I want to introduce a notion
of something called the optimal value function
so any questions about the bellman equations
all crystal clear right so if i give you an
MDP and ask you to form the valve in equation
solve it and give me the value function V?
can you do that? I will give you a ? also
can you solve it and give me a V?, may be?
kind of computers ,oh and we're at some point
I'm going to give you like MDP’s with millions
of states and ask you to compute value function
server, don't try to do that the offensive
in paper.
So maybe we should give them the head management
program, you think we should? Did he do the
head management when he did the course? I
don't think so right so this is that's a problem
that we formulated when I was once a TF or
Andy right, so he wanted people to appreciate
how hard it is for how hard is to solve dynamic
programming how hard is to solve MDP’s,
large MDP and this was a problem that was
inspired by a real life problem some sheep
or farmers like dairy farmers in New Zealand
actually solved, okay.
So they had lots of cows and they have to
decide when to milk cows and you know, when
meant to use cause for something else I got
an Indian now becoming a political statement,
right but yeah so I think sheep, okay. So
when you when you milk the cow and when do
you retire the cows you know so, they have
to figure out so let us assume that cows have
a retirement home and, so that's the process
that's a problem so then the cows could be
young you know they could be in breed able
they could be old, when they were like something
like 14 or 17different states that they had
the cows be in right, and then they have rewards
okay if you can milk the cow in a particular
state then you get so much milk, you know
if you milk a cow in a later stage the milk
comes down blah blah blah right, so whole
bunch of things and there's a small probability
that old what have been classified as old
cows also have calf, you know me so basically
they become milk able and so all kinds a very
complex situation.
And somebody actually wrote the paper out
of this, they wrote a research paper out of
solving this problem, how do you cast it as
a as an MDP and then come up with a way of
solving it because when in that case when
you actually cast it as an MDP ended up with
like a few million variables, few million
states on variables a few million states and
how do you go about solving the problem it
was not an order all clear. So what we did
was we came up with a very simplified version
of it, so we're there instead of like 17 states
there are 3 states in which the cows could
be right and the transition dynamics were
much much simplified right.
So it could from young it could become breed
able and it could pick up old and then from
old it could become breed able again so it
doesn't become n and so, so they're like a
very few transition and so on so forth but
it still turns out that you have to for computing
the exact transition probabilities right you
have to come up with a combinatorial summation
right, it's actually it turns out to be incredibly
hard to get the right transition probabilities
just the P alone and everything else is simple,
we give you what the state is we give you
what the action is right, just coming up with
the P and the are the exact closed expression
for P and
R itself turns out to be very very hard problem,
right.
And it's not it's not so there are I don't
know about 300 states or something or 158
states, it is a small problem right but computing
that transition probability even when it is
just 158 states computing the transition probability
turns out to require a combinatorial some
rights little tricky. So many people actually
fail in getting the right transition probability
they would write the correct code for solving
the problem right but then they would not
know how to compute the transition probability,
just to get you'd appreciate the difficulty
of coming up with that p and therefore, you
will appreciate why reinforcement learning
algorithms are useful because they can work
without the p.
So what is optimal here what am I talking
about as being optimal so, whenever talked
about that so far right so what is optimality
in the context of MDP’s or in the context
of RL so, we already talked about optimality
in the context of RL what is optimality in
the context of RL? I want the ? says that
for no other ? can I get a better return than
expected return than this point right, so
I want a ? right so, I want a ? that is the
best overall ? what should be the quantity
here? But that is not defined we know that
right, so the expectation over return this
does not make sense, so what should i do I
should qualify it over a state right, I should
talk about where i start the return and then
i can take expectations over that or whatever.
But even better I can do this point wise so
what do I mean by that you can say I need
something like this, ? ,thanks yeah this is
on the flight translation problems edition
one has RT capital R T is written okay, and
finishing to capital GT is written anyway
so this is this is what I am looking for right
and we know what that quantity inside there
is right, so point wise i am trying to find
max over ? V?(s) for all is right, so this
is I want a state I mean I want a policy that
achieves the maximum value for every state
right. So i am going to call this yeah i am
going to call this ? * right.
.
If I yeah I can do organized so one thing
one caveat to note here is that arc max might
not return a unique ?, that could be multiple
policies for which this maximum is achieved
in which case any one of them can be called
the optimal policy. So there is no the optimal
policy right but that is a optimal policy
that could be multiple optimal policies, just
remember that it went very simple example
I can give you think of like a grid well so,
this is something we will revisit often right.
let us say that every state has four actions
I can go up down left or right wait then every
action is going to get a reward of- one right,
and in the data ballistic world so if I go
up I will move up by one square and if you
go right I will go right by one square and
so on so forth, like in the indicator directions
or you could think of a stochastic world where
you're trying to go up with probability 0.9
I will go up the probability 0. 1,i'll just
stay where i am and you can think of this
as some wheels slipping when you have a bought
that is trying to move forward and with some
probability that we wheel slip and then you
stay in the same place and you probably have
to try moving again and again until you succeed
right.
.
So you could think of it that way right that
is a stochastic world and every time you make
an action regardless of whether you move or
not, you get a -1 right, so if we try to go
up in the top row, what will happen? You stay
there you stay there whether the action succeeds
or not will stay there and you will get a
lot of- 1 okay. So and this is an episodic
task right, the whole thing will end when
you reach the state mark G right so what will
be behaving optimally here we get to G as
quickly as possible right, so the shortest
path to G alright so, that is be the optimal
way of behaving in this world right.
So how many optimal ways are there of behaving
in this world? A policy is a mapping from
States to actions it doesn't matter very structural
but this is the mark of earnest right so we
are assuming everything is Marco is really
shouldn't depend on very start from right
so, so regardless of where I start from for
example when I am here the optimal action
is to go this way wait I do not care whether
they started here and came here or whether
i am starting here or not right regardless
of where I’m starting the action is like
that likewise, okay things become interesting
from here okay.
The number of optimal policies we have so,
any one of these states i can choose any one
of those actions right so, basically i have
about 12 states and I can choose choose any
of the two actions in those 12 states right
so, I have a huge number of optimal policies
right you can convince yourself these are
optimal because they will take me to the expected
number of steps if it is deterministic well,
I can tell you exactly how many steps it will
take me but if it is a stochastic world depending
on what is the probability of failure of the
action right I'll have some probability of
reaching the goal right, so great.
.
So there are too many optimal policies it
says something common across these entire
policies okay and you can you rephrase it?
okay not in terms of steps terms of something
else that we know net reward the expected
reward is going to be the same so for any
state regardless of what is the optimal policy
I choose to execute the value of the state
will be the same, correct is it clear? Regardless
of the policy I choose to execute the value
of the state is going to be the same correct
so i can write this and I got rid of the ?* here,
I am going to call this V*and V* is unique
given an MDP V* will be unique right.
?* need not be unique, but regardless of how
many different ?* you have right V* is going
to be the same whichever ?* you consider V*
will be the same so regardless of V?* regardless
of the ?* you choose I am going to call the
optimal value function as V* okay, so this
is called the so this is an optimal policy
its optimal value function is I said ,there's
only one thing which you guys should be asking
me now how do I know that the same ? will
reach the max across all s, so if you have
finite MDP’s, it is actually straightforward
to show that okay if you have continuous MDP’s
right then it becomes a little trickier, so
we will discuss this when I am actually starting
the proofs in the next class, why is it that
there exists a optimal policy at all right,
so we will discuss this in the next class
when I'm talking about proves right.
.
So right now, we will try to do the equivalent
of Bellman equations for V* right, I mean
likewise i can define an optimal value function
for q, what would be the optimal value function
for q, yeah another solution is there something
that sound right, what is problem here so
we need to put that ? thing here right, so
what I what I want you to appreciate here
is that even though I am talking about optimal
policies, I still the first action it take
easy right the first actually take is A, always
here whether I am talking about optimal so,
it is only after i take a I behave optimally
so that is why this max is after, in fact
I can remove the maximum here and I can insert
it anything that comes before it is it not
influenced by the max right.
Because I take a fixed action it is something
which you have to keep in mind so whenever
you talk about Q*S,A right, the A is still
fixed it might not be the best A to do right
in fact, I can have a Q* a defined for this
action here, wait I can have a Q* here defined
for this action also for each one of these
actions I can have a Q* defined right, this
is it so the Q* of the down action will essentially
be -1 + V* of going from here to the goal,
right in the Q* of this action will be 1 +
V* of going here assuming is deterministic,
otherwise it will be 0.9 -1+0.9 times the
value of going from here and 0.9 times the
value of going from if it is sarcastic right.
so I can think of defining Q*for even sub
optimal action this is one thing if I want
to keep in mind so it's not like Q* is defined
only for optimal actions let there, okay great,
so now we have these things so let us try
to see what we can do so, I want to do v star
of yes ray I want to find V*(s), so what would
V*(s) equal to? Do you think in terms of Q*?
So what do you think V*(s) will be in terms
of Q*, so what is Q* tell me? If I take action
A and behave optimally thereafter right so,
what can V* be, I mean that is essentially
behaving optimally from the current state.
Let say I am going to look at okay which one
whatever gives me the best reward on taking
A and then behaving optimally thereafter right
so think about what this expression is? This
expression is essentially okay I behave according
to A and after that I behave optimally right,
so that is essentially this expression right
and I am taking a max here which essentially
means said okay, which is the action that
gives me this? The best of this expression
and that I cannot behave more optimally than
that, because it is only the first action
I have a choice here after that I'm assuming
and behaving optimally whatever is optimal
behavior right.
So i am not talking about the recovering the
optimal behavior yet right, I'm only talking
about finding what the optimal value function
is right, I am assuming after-action A and
behaving optimally, so now the only thing
i need to figure out is what is action A and
I need to pick that action A says that when
you add the reward for taking mediate or what
for taking action A and the return for behaving
optimally they are after I get the most. So
this is essentially very intuitive way of
defining what the optimal value function is
now I can expand this you can say it's max
over A summation s prime and that is what
max over ? is say max over ?V? V*sort of the
V*is prime.
.
e
This is how we got that so, this is called
the bellman optimality equation. For V* likewise
you can write a bell but optimality equation
for, you start have to be why not wait whether
it some policy there is no question of some
policy will give you a higher policy even
why I given you all the optimal policies tell
me which one will do that? Just think about
it if that is some policy that will do that
then I will basically change the action to
that I mean that has to be optimum right if
there is going right this does not have the
same values going up going up as a higher
value than going right, then going up has
to be optimal going right cannot be optimal
because then if I do the max only one will
apply the other one won't appear right.
so one other thing so I have been talking
only about deterministic optimal policies
right I said there are like there are 12elements
and there are two options there did not be
so, as long as I have a policy which are saying
only non zero probabilities to the optimal
actions right that is also an optimal policy
so, in this state I can choose with probability
0.5 to go up or probability 0.5 to go right,
right so, 0.5 do up, 0.5 go right that is
also an optimal policy right it could be any
combination as long as I have zero probability
for going right or going down right then I
am self happy then it is an optimal policy
right so, there is an infinite number of optimal
policies is an infinite number of twin powers
itself, is it clear? Okay.
so nowhere is the next question I want to
ask so given a policy so Q* value function
how will you recover optimal policy from that
because, I give you v star how you recover
an optimal policy from that so I have to know
figure out what action I have to take in each
state right and I have to take that action
that achieves the max right so, what I mean
by achieves the max so in the case of V* actually
take an action figure out where I will end
up it right, and take that action that gives
me the max over that right so, what I mean
by where I land up at so I pick some action
right then i sum over s prime sorry, so this
is the utility for taking an action right.
.
so I have to pick an action that gives me
so given a V* this is how I will recover a
PI star right yeah depends on how you how
you implement the arc max that if the ark
max you can write it such a way that you will
return any of the maximizes then you will
get a deterministic policy or you can return
your arm access that it returns all the maximizes
then you can think of having some kind of
uniform probability distribution over the
Maximize it can be uniform or it could be
one way or but if, you think of arc max is
returning some arbitrarily returning one of
the maximizes will get a deterministic policy
right this is one way of recovering optimal
policies from the optimal value function okay.
so the little trickier I still need to know
p and c need to know the expected values and
other things even if somebody gives me the
value function I still need to know the rest
of the parameters of the MDP for me to recover
the optimal policy. But suppose somebody gives
me the Q function how I will recommend the
optimal policy, we think about look at the
expression there right in the arc max is exactly
this right. so
if i give you the cue functions if I give
me Q* I do not need all this that what I am
doing that is essentially looking at one step
right if I do a okay what will happen? Right.
so I am looking at the outcome and then trying
to make the decision the best decision based
on that outcome right but here the Q* I do
not even have to do that one step look at
it right I can just be greedy with respect
to my current Q*and I will ?* makes sense
so, if i give you V*and Q* now we can know
how to find ?* and we also we spoke about
how we can solve the bellman equation for
V ? and Q ?, can you solve the bellman equation
like that for V*and Q*, so I have a system
of n equations in n variables same thing as
before can I solve it what's the problem?
it's not linear right so it says i have this
max here it makes it the non linear system
of equations so you'll have to figure out
how we are going to solve it right.
So this is what we will look at in the next
class the next layer what I will do is first
show that well in multiple ways so that V?
is unique and then show that V* is unique
right, and then come up with a talk about
multiple ways of solving for we started well
not only this will b V? can we'll talk about
multiple ways of solving for V*, in fact the
rest of the course in some senses figuring
out multiple ways of solving for V*and Q*
under different assumptions okay, how much
information you have how much data you have
and so on so forth right, so great so any
questions?